## Michael Murrietta

2167 E Decatur Ave, Fresno, California 93720 | (559)708-6029 | mmurrietta8@gmail.com www.linkedin.com/pub/michael-murrietta/84/69/872/ https://github.com/murrietta

### **Data Scientist | Communicator**

I am a recent graduate of the Master of Science in Data Science program at Southern Methodist University with 5 years' experience in analytics. My focus is to communicate analytical solutions to influence impactful changes. I enjoy helping others wherever I can, from building a classification model to fixing an old wooden fence.

## **Skills:**

- Interpersonal Skills: Data analytics can be a catalyst for impactful changes but fails to be without proper communication. I speak English AND tech, enabling me to work with influencers to elaborate vision into wellspecified solutions.
- **Statistics:** Thorough understanding of fundamental concepts and how to use them to understand business. A solid background in linear models and how to adapt this simple yet powerful model to many situations.
- Machine Learning: Experience with many models in many problem spaces: regression, classification, using many
  models from support vector machines to recurrent neural networks. Versed in the standards like train-test split,
  cross validation, data augmentation, feature engineering, metric selection, countermeasures, and others.
- Programming: I have spent much of my work and free time writing code for the past 6 years
  - Python (5+ years) at work, home, and school (numpy, scipy, sklearn, matplotlib, pandas, keras, tensorflow, spaCy, NLTK, PySpark, statstools, and other packages).
  - Visual Basic (5+) at work, and home. Mostly for automating Excel and Outlook. Has been a crucial help when working with more Excel oriented colleagues.
  - R (3+) and SAS (2) during grad school, at work, and at home. I favor R for statistical analyses.
  - o Matlab/Octave (2+) and Mathematica (2) during undergrad and at home.
  - Javascript (1.5) combined with HTML and CSS for personal and academic projects.
  - Others not listed: I've used around a dozen different languages in some capacity before.
- Scripting: Using bash, cmd, powershell, or python. I can easily write scripts to call from the command line.
- Data Tools: SQL for 4 years, Apache Spark, and MongoDb for 1.5 years.
- Cloud Computing: Google Cloud Products (GCP) mostly but have also used Amazon Web Services (AWS).
- Visualization: Using D3.js, P5.js, Processing, Open Frameworks, Tableau, and PowerBI.
- Medical Informatics: Working with ICD 9/10, CPT codes for 4 years, HL7 data transfer protocol for 3 years.

# Accomplishments

- Built data validation and integration pipeline using SQL and Python. Imports new data and identifies any suspicious values before incorporating in on-going analyses. Estimated saving of 0.13 FTEs.
- Saved an employer ~\$90k/year by building an Ongoing Practitioner Performance Evaluation (OPPE) tool using existing software.
- Data warehouse development and deployment in a hospital organization to enable self-service analytics.
- Collaborated on a sepsis early warning system by developing a custom classification algorithm.
- Developed and deployed C. difficile risk calculator by adapting research paper results to a different population.
- Developed and deployed an analytics pipeline to accurately identify Ventilator Associated Events.

#### **Education**

- Master of Science in Data Science: Southern Methodist University (SMU)
- Bachelor of Arts in Mathematics: California State University Fresno (CSUF)

# Experience

| GE Healthcare Partners (GEHCP) Associate Consultant - Analytics, Full-time   | July 2018 to Present   |
|--|--|
| <ul> <li>Analytics support multiple workstreams</li> <li>Build data-based tools for client use</li> <li>ActionOI/Truven benchmarking for clinical partners</li> </ul>  | <ul> <li>General database administration</li> <li>Ad hoc analyses as needed</li> <li>Migration and optimization of Excel-based tools to SQL to enable rapid assessments</li> </ul>                             |
| Valley Children's Hospital (VCH)   | December 2016 to July 2018   |
| Clinical Decision Support Coordinator, Full-time   | Infection Prevention Department  |
| <ul> <li>Analytical support of org-wide initiatives</li> <li>Automate data reporting structure in VB</li> <li>Ad hoc analyses as needed</li> </ul>   | <ul> <li>Collaborate on SQL Server data warehouse</li> <li>Statistical support for clinical research</li> <li>Support previously developed solution for OPPE</li> </ul>  |
| Valley Children's Hospital (VCH)   | February 2016 to December 2016   |
| Data Analyst, Full-time  | Quality and Performance Improvement  |
| <ul> <li>Consult on and develop solution for OPPE</li> </ul>   | Ad hoc analyses as needed  |
| <ul> <li>Manage continuous improvement project</li> </ul>  | Collaborate on data warehouse development  |
| Valley Children's Hospital (VCH)  System Support Specialist – Periop, Full-time  • Automate regular reports using Excel and VBA  • Creation of audit-aiding reports boosting productivity and accuracy of team | November 2014 to February 2016 Perioperative Services Department  Write SAP Crystal Reports and perform Ad hoc analyses as needed Administrator for clinical endoscopy procedure software (Olympus Endoworks). |
| California Casualty Management Company (CCMC)  | September 2014 to November 2014  |
| Ratings and Statistical Analyst, Full-time   | Actuarial Department   |
| <ul> <li>Competitive analysis on similar products</li> <li>Maintenance and update of simulation models</li> </ul>  | <ul> <li>Simulation of overall price change effects<br/>using Excel and VBA</li> </ul>   |
| Valley Children's Hospital (VCH)   | January 2012 to September 2014   |
| SPD Technician III, Full-time  | Sterile Processing Department  |
| <ul> <li>Decontamination, packaging,<br/>sterilization, and storage of instruments</li> <li>Allocate supplies for surgical case carts</li> </ul>   | <ul> <li>Sterilizer testing, cleaning and maintenance</li> <li>Occasional acting team lead</li> <li>Training new technicians.</li> </ul>   |